<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE akomantoso SYSTEM "../../../../../../schemas/akomantoso10.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../../styles/akomantoso.xsl"?>
<akomantoso xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/1.0">
    <bill>
        <meta>
            <identification source="FV">
                <Work>
                    <uri href="/zaf/bill/2003-09-04/76"/>
                    <date date="2003-09-04" name="Enactment"/>
                    <author href="#Par" as="#Author"/>
                </Work>
                <Expression>
                    <uri href="/zaf/bill/2003-09-04/76/en@20051231"/>
                    <date date="2005-12-31" name="Repeal"/>
                    <author href="#FV" as="#Jurist"/>
                </Expression>
                <Manifestation>
                    <uri href="/zaf/bill/2003-09-04/76/en@20051231.akn"/>
                    <date date="2006-09-11" name="XMLConversion"/>
                    <author href="#FV" as="#Editor"/>
                </Manifestation>
            </identification>
            <publication date="2003-09-04" name="Government Gazette 25437" showAs="Government Gazette # 25437" />
            <lifecycle source="FV">
                <event id="evn1" source="org01" date="2005-08-29" type="Generation" />
                <event id="evn2" source="pas01" date="2005-12-31" type="Repeal" />
            </lifecycle>
            <references source="FV">
                <Original   href="/zaf/bill/2003-09-04/76/en.akn"           id="org01"       showAs="Bill #76/2003" />
                <PassiveRef href="/zaf/act/2005-12-31/97/en.akn"            id="pas01"       showAs="Act #97/2005"/>
                <Person href="/ontology/person/editors/ita.Fabio.Vitali"    id="FV"          showAs="Fabio Vitali"/>
                <Organization href="/ontology/organization/ken.Parliament"  id="Par"         showAs="Parliament"/>
                <Role   href="/ontology/role/Author"                        id="Author"      showAs="Author of Document"/>
                <Role   href="/ontology/role/Editor"                        id="Editor"      showAs="Editor of Document"/>
                <Role   href="/ontology/role/Jurist"                        id="Jurist"      showAs="Jurist of Document"/>
            </references>
        </meta>
        <preface>
            <p class="important">REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA</p>
            <p class="important">
                <ActTitle>TRADITIONAL LEADERSHIP AND GOVERNANCE FRAMEWORK BILL</ActTitle>
            </p>
            <p class="center">(As introduced in the National Assembly as a section 76 Bill;
                explanatory summary of Bill published in Government Gazette No. 25437 of 4 September
                2003)</p>
            <p class="center">(The English text is the official text of the Bill)</p>
            <p class="center">(<ActProponent>MINISTER FOR PROVINCIAL AND LOCAL
                GOVERNMENT</ActProponent>)</p>
            <p class="important">
                <ActType>BILL</ActType>
            </p>
            <p>To <ActPurpose>provide for the recognition of traditional communities; to provide for
                    the establishment and recognition of traditional councils; to provide for the
                    functions and roles of traditional leaders; to provide a statutory framework for
                    leadership positions within the institution of traditional leadership, the
                    recognition of traditional leaders and the removal from office of traditional
                    leaders; to provide for houses of traditional leaders; to provide for dispute
                    resolution and the establishment of the Commission on Traditional Leadership
                    Disputes and Claims; and to provide for matters connected
                therewith.</ActPurpose>
            </p>
        </preface>
        <preamble>
            <p class="important">PREAMBLE</p>
            <p>WHEREAS the State, in accordance with the Constitution, seeks—</p>
            <ul id="ul1">
                <li>to set out a national framework and norms and standards that will define the
                    place and role of traditional leadership within the new system of democratic
                    governance;</li>
                <li>to transform the institution in line with constitutional imperatives; and</li>
                <li>to restore the integrity and legitimacy of the institution of traditional
                    leadership in line with customary law and practices;</li>
            </ul>
            <p>AND WHEREAS the South African indigenous people consist of a diversity of cultural
                communities;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS the Constitution recognises—</p>
            <ul id="ul2">
                <li>the institution, status and role of traditional leadership according to
                    customary law; and</li>
                <li>a traditional community that observes a system of customary law;</li>
            </ul>
            <p>AND WHEREAS—</p>
            <ul id="ul3">
                <li>the State must respect, protect and promote the institution of traditional
                    leadership in accordance with the dictates of democracy in South Africa;</li>
                <li>the institution of traditional leadership must be transformed to be in harmony
                    with the Constitution and the Bill of Rights so that democratic governance and
                    the values of an open and democratic society may be promoted; and</li>
                <li>the institution of traditional leadership must <ul id="ul4">
                        <li>promote freedom, human dignity and the achievement of equality and
                            non-sexism;</li>
                        <li>derive its mandate and primary authority from applicable customary law
                            and practices;</li>
                        <li>strive to enhance tradition and culture;</li>
                        <li>promote nation building and harmony and peace amongst people;</li>
                        <li>promote the principles of co-operative governance in its interaction
                            with all spheres of government and organs of state; and</li>
                        <li>promote an efficient, effective and fair dispute-resolution system, and
                            a fair system of administration of justice, as envisaged in applicable
                            legislation,</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>BE IT THEREFORE ENACTED by the Parliament of the Republic of South Africa, as
                follows:—</p>
            <p class="important">ARRANGEMENT OF SECTIONS</p>
            <toc>
                <tocitem href="#chap01" level="1">CHAPTER 1 INTERPRETATION AND APPLICATION</tocitem>
                <tocitem href="#art01" level="2">1. Definitions and application</tocitem>
                <tocitem href="#chap02" level="1">CHAPTER 2 TRADITIONAL COMMUNITIES AND TRADITIONAL
                    COUNCILS</tocitem>
                <tocitem href="#art02" level="2">2. Recognition of traditional communities</tocitem>
            </toc>
        </preamble>
        <clauses>
            <chapter id="chap01">
                <num>CHAPTER 1</num>
                <title>INTERPRETATION AND APPLICATION</title>
                <article id="art01">
                    <num>1.</num>
                    <title>Definitions and application</title>
                    <clause id="art01-cla01">
                        <num>(1)</num>
                        <p>In this Act, unless the context indicates otherwise— </p>
                        <ul id="ul5">
                            <li>
                                <def>area of jurisdiction</def> means the area of jurisdiction
                                designated for a traditional community and traditional council that
                                have been recognised as provided for in <ref href="#art2">sections
                                2</ref> and <ref href="#art3">3</ref>;</li>
                            <li>
                                <def>Commission</def> means the commission established by <ref
                                    href="#art20">section 20</ref>;</li>
                            <li>
                                <def>customary institution or structure</def> means those
                                institutions or structures established in terms of customary law;</li>
                            <li>
                                <def>district house of traditional leaders</def> means a district
                                house of traditional leaders provided for in <ref
                                    href="#art15-cla02">section 15(b)</ref>;</li>
                            <li>
                                <def>district municipality</def> means a district municipality as
                                defined in <ref href="/act/1998/117_en.xml">section 1 of the
                                    Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, 1998 (Act No. 117 of
                                    1998);</ref>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <def>headman or headwoman</def> means a traditional leader who— <ol id="ol1">
                                    <li>is under the authority of, or exercises authority within the
                                        area of jurisdiction of, a principal traditional leader in
                                        accordance with customary law; and</li>
                                    <li>is recognised as such in terms of this Act;</li>
                                </ol>
                            </li>
                            <li>...</li>
                        </ul>
                    </clause>
                    <clause id="art01-cla02">
                        <num>(2)</num>
                        <p> Nothing contained in this Act may be construed as precluding members of
                            a traditional community from addressing a traditional leader by the
                            traditional title accorded to him or her by custom, but such traditional
                            title does not derogate from, or add anything to, the status, role and
                            functions of a traditional leader as provided for in this Act.</p>
                    </clause>
                </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chap02">
                <num>CHAPTER 2</num>
                <title>TRADITIONAL COMMUNITIES AND TRADITIONAL COUNCILS</title>
                <article id="art02">
                    <num>2.</num>
                    <title>Recognition of traditional communities</title>
                    <clause id="art02-cla01">
                        <num>(1)</num>
                        <p>A community may be recognised as a traditional community if it—</p>
                        <ol id="ol2">
                            <li>is subject to a system of traditional leadership in terms of that
                                community’s own customary rules; and</li>
                            <li>observes a system of customary law.</li>
                        </ol>
                    </clause>
                    <clause id="art02-cla02">
                        <num>(2)</num>
                        <p>The Premier of a province may, by notice in the Provincial Gazette, in
                            accordance with provincial legislation and after consultation with the
                            provincial house of traditional leaders in the province and the
                            community concerned, recognise a community envisaged in subsection (1)
                            as a traditional community.</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause id="art02-cla03">
                        <num>(3)</num>
                        <p>A traditional community must transform and adapt applicable customs and
                            customary law so as to comply with the relevant principles contained in
                            the Bill of Rights in the Constitution.</p>
                    </clause>
                </article>
            </chapter>
        </clauses>
    </bill>
</akomantoso>
