<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE akomantoso SYSTEM "../../../../../schemas/akomantoso10.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../styles/akomantoso.xsl"?>
<akomantoso xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/1.0">
	<debaterecord>
		<meta>
			<identification source="FV">
				<Work>
					<uri href="/ken/minutes/1995-10-31"/>
					<date date="1995-10-31" name="Generation"/>
					<author href="#Par" as="#Author"/>
				</Work>
				<Expression>
					<uri href="/ken/minutes/1995-10-31/en"/>
					<date date="2007-05-31" name="Writing"/>
					<author href="#FV" as="#Editor"/>
				</Expression>
				<Manifestation>
					<uri href="/ken/minutes/1995-10-31/en.akn"/>
					<date date="2007-05-31" name="Publication"/>
					<author href="#FV" as="#Editor"/>
				</Manifestation>
			</identification>
				<publication date="1995-11-01" name="internal" showAs="Internal Circulation Only"/>
			<references source="FV">
				<Person href="/ontology/person/editors/ita.Fabio.Vitali"    id="FV"          showAs="Fabio Vitali"/>
				<Organization href="/ontology/organization/ken.Parliament"  id="Par"         showAs="Parliament"/>
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Smith"       id="Smith"       showAs="Mr Smith" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Mzee"        id="Mzee"        showAs="Prof. Mzee" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Kofa"        id="Kofa"        showAs="Mr. Kofa" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Manga"       id="Manga"       showAs="Mr. Manga" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.MakOnyango"  id="MakOnyango"  showAs="Mr. Mak'Onyango" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Manduku"     id="Manduku"     showAs="Mr. Manduku" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Achola"      id="Achola"      showAs="Mr. Achola" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Criticos"    id="Criticos"    showAs="Mr. Criticos" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Aluoch"      id="Aluoch"      showAs="Mr. Aluoch" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Nthenge"     id="Nthenge"     showAs="Mr. Nthenge" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Moiben"      id="Moiben"      showAs="Mr. Moiben" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Barmasai"    id="Barmasai"    showAs="Mr. Barmasai" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Nyagah"      id="Nyagah"      showAs="Mr. Nyagah" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Maore"       id="Maore"       showAs="Mr. Maore" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Mwaura"      id="Mwaura"      showAs="Mr. Nyagah" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Obwocha"     id="Obwocha"     showAs="Mr. Obwocha" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Shikuku"     id="Shikuku"     showAs="Mr. Shikuku" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Kiluta"      id="Kiluta"      showAs="Col. Kiluta" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Karan"       id="Karan"       showAs="Mr. Karan" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.LwaliOyondi" id="LwaliOyondi" showAs="Dr. Lwali-Oyondi" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Sunkuli"     id="Sunkuli"     showAs="Dr. Wako" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Farah"       id="Farah"       showAs="Mr. Farah" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Falana"      id="Falana"      showAs="Mr. Falana" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Mungai"      id="Mungai"      showAs="R.K. Mungai" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Angatia"     id="Angatia"     showAs="Mr. Angatia" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Wetangula"   id="Wetangula"   showAs="Mr. Wetangula" />
				<Person href="/ontology/person/ken/MP/ken.John.Wako"        id="Wako"        showAs="Mr. Wako" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/Author"                        id="Author"      showAs="Author of Document"/>
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/Editor"                        id="Editor"      showAs="Editor of Document"/>
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/Speaker"             id="S"           showAs="Mr. Speaker" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MS"                  id="MS"          showAs="Minister of State, Office of the President" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/AMS"                 id="AMS"         showAs="The Assistant Minister of State, Office of the President" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MFA"                 id="MFA"         showAs="Minister for Foreign Affairs and International Co-operation" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/AMFA"                id="AMFA"        showAs="The Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs and International Co-operation" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MH"                  id="MH"          showAs="Minister for Health" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/AMH"                 id="AMH"         showAs="The Assistant Minister for Health" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MCI"                 id="MCI"         showAs="Minister for Commerce and Industry" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/AMCI"                id="AMCI"        showAs="The Assistant Minister for Commerce and Industry" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MTI"                 id="MTI"         showAs="Minister for Tourism and Industry" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/TDS"                 id="TDS"         showAs="Temporary Deputy Speaker" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MTW"                 id="MTW"         showAs="Minister for Tourism and Wildlife" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/MPWH"                id="MPWH"        showAs="Minister for Public Works and Housing" />
				<Role   href="/ontology/role/political/AMPWH"               id="AMPWH"       showAs="The Assistant Minister for Public Works and Housing" />
			</references>
			<notes source="FV">
				<note id="not01">
					<p>Provided as is from MS Word files</p>
				</note>
				<note id="not02">
					<p>I only imagine the Speaker's name to be Mr. Smith. </p>
				</note>
			</notes>
		</meta>
		<preface>
			<p class="important">NATIONAL ASSEMBLY</p>
			<p class="important">OFFICIAL REPORT</p>
			<p class="center">Tuesday, 31st October, 1995<noteref href="#not01" num="1" /></p>
			<p class="center">The House met at 2.30 p.m.</p>
			<p class="center">[Mr. Speaker in the Chair]</p>
		</preface>
		<debate>
			<subdivision id="prayers">
				<title>PRAYERS</title>
			</subdivision>
			<subdivision id="papers">
				<title>PAPERS LAID</title>
				<other id="other01">
					<p> The following Papers were laid on the Table:-</p>
					<ul id="ul1">
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Jomo Kenyatta University College of
							Agriculture and Technology for the year ended 30th June, 1990 and the
							Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General (Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Higher Education Loans Fund for the year
							ended 30th June, 1982 and the Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General
							(Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Higher Education Loans Fund for the year
							ended 30th June, 1983 and the Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General
							(Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Higher Education Loans Fund for the year
							ended 30th June, 1984 and the Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General
							(Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Higher Education Loans Fund for the year
							ended 30th June, 1985 and the Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General
							(Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Higher Education Loans Fund for the year
							ended 30th June, 1986 and the Certificate thereon by the Auditor-General
							(Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of University Students Accommodation Board
							(USAB) for the year ended 30th June, 1985 and the Certificate thereon by
							the Auditor-General (Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of University Students Accommodation Board
							(USAB) for the year ended 30th June, 1986 and the Certificate thereon by
							the Auditor-General (Corporations)</li>
						<li>Annual Report and Accounts of Kenya National Examinations Council for
							the year ended 30th June, 1994 and the Certificate thereon by the
							Auditor-General (Corporations)</li>
					</ul>
					<comment>By the Assistant Minister for Education (Mr. Lengees) on behalf of the
						Minister for Education</comment>
				</other>
			</subdivision>
			<subdivision id="notices">
				<title>NOTICE OF MOTION</title>
				<subdivision id="notice01">
					<title>EXPORT OF MANGROVE POLES</title>
					<speech by="Mzee">
						<from>Prof. Mzee</from>
						<p>Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to give notice of the following Motion:-</p>
						<p>THAT, since the ban (for the last 20 years) of export of mangrove poles
							has resulted in deterioration of mangrove forest and since the ecology
							of mangrove forest requires regular harvest to stimulate regeneration,
							this House urges the Government to lift the ban on the export of
							mangrove poles.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
			</subdivision>
			<subdivision id="qa">
				<title>ORAL ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</title>
				<subdivision id="que803a">
					<title>BANDITRY MENACE IN GALOLE</title>
					<question by="Kofa" to="MS">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Kofa asked the Minister of State, Office of the President</p>
						<ul id="ul2">
							<li>whether he is aware that Councillor Abdi Sole of Asako Location was
								seriously injured and two homeguards were shot dead and their guns
								stolen while pursuing bandits on 20th May, 1995;</li>
							<li>who instructed these people to pursue the heavily armed bandits;
								and,</li>
							<li>if the Ministry can ensure that the families of the deceased
								homeguards are compensated and that Councillor Sole's medical
								expenses are paid in full.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Speaker</from>
						<p> <noteref num="2" href="#not02"/>Anybody from the Office of the President?</p>
					</speech>
					<answer by="Manga" as="AMS">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the answer is being prepared. The Minister is coming
							to give the answer.</p>
					</answer>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que824">
					<title>REVIVAL OF E.A. COMMUNITY</title>
					<question by="MakOnyango" to="MFA">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Mak'Onyango asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs and International
							Co-operation</p>
						<ul id="ul3">
							<li>what bottlenecks are delaying the revival of the East African
								Community as mapped out in the Arusha Accord of the 1st December,
								1994, between the Heads of State of Kenya, Uganda and Tanzania; and,</li>
							<li>to what extent is Kenya, as a country, to blame for the delay.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer by="Manduku" as="AMFA">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to request the House to allow us to answer this
							Question on Thursday, 2nd of November, 1995.</p>
						<p>Thank you.</p>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Mak'Onyango, are you objecting?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="MakOnyango">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Yes, Mr. Speaker, Sir, I will object very strongly because this Question
							was due here last week, and I was told that the Question be pushed to
							this week. How long are we going to be pushed before we get an
						answer?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Finally, to Thursday; no more. </p>
					</speech>
					<comment>Question deferred</comment>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que630">
					<title>DEATH OF MS. MUIRURI</title>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Robert Mungai not here? Next question, Mr. Owino Achola.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que699">
					<title>THEFT OF HOSPITAL DRUGS</title>
					<question by="Achola" to="MH">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Achola asked the Minister for Health</p>
						<ul id="ul4">
							<li>whether he is aware that during 1994/95 fiscal year alone, drugs,
								medical supplies and various equipment amounting to over Kshs13
								million were stolen from Migori District Hospital; and,</li>
							<li>what action does he contemplate taking to bring the culprits to book
								and save wananchi from perpetual lack of drugs and diagnostic
								services. </li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer by="Criticos" as="AMH">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to reply.</p>
						<ul id="ul5">
							<li>
								<p>It is not true that during the year 1994/95 drugs, medical
									supplies and various equipment amounting to over Kshs13 million
									were stolen from Migori District Hospital.</p>
								<p>But I am aware that during this period drugs worth Kshs22,000
									were stolen from the drug store of the hospital. Investigations
									carried out led to the arrest of three hospital staff, who have
									been charged and the case is pending before Migori Senior
									Magistrate's Court.</p>
								<p>I am also aware that electric calculators worth Kshs2,900 and a
									typewriter worth Kshs59,800 were stolen. The reports were made
									to the Migori Police Station but to date no arrests or
									recoveries have been made. </p>
								<p>In April 1995, a new photocopier worth Kshs289,000 was stolen and
									investigations by police officers led to the arrest of four
									hospital staff and recovery of the photocopier. The officers
									have been charged and the Ministry interdicted them. The case is
									still pending before the court. </p>
								<p>The watchman who was on duty has since been charged and the case
									is pending before Migori court. The total value of all these
									stolen items is Kshs455,190.</p>
							</li>
							<li>The measures the Ministry has taken to curb the thefts are:- 
								<ul id="ul6">
									<li>The institution of strict control measures on delivery,
										storage and issuing of drugs, medical supplies and
										equipment.</li>
									<li>The hospital has now been fenced.</li>
									<li>The drug store has been burglar-proofed.</li>
									<li>The staff suspected of being involved in thefts have been
										reshuffled.</li>
									<li>The County Council staff who were staying in the hospital
										compound premises have been removed.</li>
									<li>The Administration Police Officers have been deployed to
										guard the hospital compound.</li>
								</ul>
							</li>
						</ul>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Just before I allow Members to ask supplementary questions, Mr.
							Assistant Minister, you said in part (a) that there are some cases in
							court. Do you have the case numbers and who are the parties?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I do not <span class="unknown">Mr. Criticos</span> have the relevant information
							regarding the parties concerned but, obviously, it is the Ministry of
							Health versus the culprits.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Achola">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I think the Assistant Minister has tried to hide some
							of the facts by understating the actual amount involved. He has only
							talked about Kshs450,000, but my records show that over Kshs13 million
							has been stolen. Could the Assistant Minister inform the House as to
							what exactly is going on? When will these people be charged and what is
							the case number of the people involved? The thefts in Migori hospital
							have been going on for a long time and nothing seems to be happening.
							Thieves are being recycled, as he puts it, and this is not good enough
							for our people.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, first, I would like to ask the hon. Member to give me
							a copy of his records which indicate theft of equipment worth Kshs13
							million. I really would like that information because we, in the
							Ministry, are not aware. Secondly, about the reshuffling of the people,
							we cannot discharge people from the service of the Ministry when they
							have not been caught red-handed and when there is no evidence against
							them by which they can be charged in court. So, if there is any doubt,
							we try and move them to other areas because they have not been proven
							guilty. Therefore, we cannot assume someone is guilty.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Aluoch">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, in the answer given by the Assistant Minister, part
							(v) states that the County Council staff who are staying in the hospital
							compound premises have been removed. This is misleading the House. Only
							last Monday, we were attending a DDC meeting and we were discussing when
							the County Council staff will leave the hospital compound because, this
							is what is contributing to the thefts as well. </p>
						<p>The Chairman of the County Council is still there, the Clerk to the
							Council and the rest of the Council staff are occupying the houses that
							the hospital staff should be using. They cannot even install an X-ray
							machine because the council staff are still in the compound. What are
							you going to do to remove them instead of telling us that they are not
							there? Stop misleading this House!</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, we are not aware that the County Council is using
							Ministry of Health houses. If the hon. Member can furnish us with the
							names of the people concerned, the Ministry will then take the
							appropriate action to evict them.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Nthenge">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. Do you not agree with me that the
							hon. Member has told the Assistant Minister even the titles of the
							people occupying these houses? One is the Town Clerk, the other one is
							the Chairman of the County Council. What other information does he
						need?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> I agree with you!</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I got two names; the Town Clerk and the Chairman of
							the County Council. I do not know whether these are the only ones or
							there are others. I was just asking about the others. You have my
							assurance that those people will be evicted immediately.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Achola">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Thank you, Mr. Speaker, Sir. I think I would like the Assistant Minister
							to assure this House that something is going to be done to stop the
							theft of drugs from Migori Hospital. Even the local pharmacies around
							are selling, in broad daylight, drugs from Government Stores and nothing
							is being done about that. The police are not arresting anybody. What are
							you going to do, Mr. Assistant Minister?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I have said, on numerous occasions, that we would like
							support from the local community. They should also keep a watchful eye
							on these people. I have given you six measures that we have taken to
							stop the theft of drugs. However, the local community and the medical
							board which is there should also be actively involved in looking after
							our drugs because they belong to us in general.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Next Question, Mr. Moiben.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que801">
					<title>COMMISSIONING OF HEALTH CENTRE</title>
					<question by="Moiben" to="MH">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Moiben asked the Minister for Health</p>
						<ul id="ul7">
							<li>when Saboti Health Centre will be operational and officially opened;
								and,</li>
							<li>when the Health Centre will be supplied with electricity.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer as="AMH" by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to reply.</p>
						<ul id="ul8">
							<li>My Ministry intended to complete and operationalize Saboti Health
								Centre during the 1994/95 financial year. However, due to the
								inadequate funds and escalation of the costs over the period of 1991
								- 93, the project could not be completed as planned and it is about
								95 per cent complete. The project period expired and, hence, there
								is no provision in the current financial year for the remaining
								funds to be allocated. My Ministry is in the process of obtaining
								funds to fully complete and equip the health centre, after which it
								will be operational and officially opened.</li>
							<li>Within the present contract for the health centre, there is a
								provision for a generator which should be adequate to provide
								electricity for <span class="unknown">The Assistant Minister for Health</span> the services
								that will require electricity. Electricity will, therefore, be
								supplied to the health centre as soon as funds for the installation
								of generators are provided.</li>
						</ul>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Moiben">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the Trans-Nzoia DDC approved that electricity be
							supplied to this hospital way back in 1991. Can the Assistant Minister
							confirm when this will be done? The hospital was 95 per cent completed
							way back in 1991.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Criticos">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, like I said earlier, when the funds are allocated,
							this will be done. We cannot supply electricity without funds.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Next Question, Mr. Nyagah!</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que605">
					<title>LOANS FOR GACHOKA RESIDENTS</title>
					<question by="Nyagah" to="MCI">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Nyagah asked the Minister for Commerce and Industry</p>
						<ul id="ul9">
							<li>when he will consider extending trade loan facilities to the people
								of Gachoka Constituency to enable them start small businesses; and,</li>
							<li>how many traders from Gachoka were given such loans between 1988 and
								1995.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer by="Barmasai" as="AMCI">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to reply.</p>
						<ul id="ul10">
							<li>Trade loan facilities have already been extended to the people of
								Gachoka Constituency.</li>
							<li>Over 200 traders have received such loans between 1988 and
							1995.</li>
						</ul>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Nyagah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, by the year 2000, there will be 33 million people in
							Kenya. To alleviate rural-urban migration, we need to look after that
							group that lives in the rural areas so that they do not feel the need to
							move into the urban areas. How much of that money was given to the 200
							people between 1988 and 1995, given the fact that the Government
							provision for this, in any given year, is not more than K£250,000? If
							you were to divide that per province, each province is entitled to less
							than K£62,500?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Barmasai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, it really depends on what the hon. Member refers to
							when he talks of small businesses. If it includes small industries, then
							what they have been given is Kshs24 million.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Maore">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, can the Assistant Minister confirm or deny that nearly
							all of the 200 members he has talked about are those people who received
							the Kenya Rural Enterprise legal peanuts ranging between Kshs5,000 and
							Kshs10,000, just prior to the 1992 election campaigns?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Barmasai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the 200 people I am referring to are those ones who
							got the loan from the Joint Loans Board and the Kenya Industrial Estates
							(KIE) and Industrial and Commercial Development Corporation (ICDC) for
							small industries.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Nyagah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, this is of great concern to Kenyans. We need to
							empower the small businessmen at home. That is what the economy is
							dependent on. </p>
						<p>Can the Assistant Minister break up what was given in form of loans by
							the KIE, and what was given in form of trade loans by the Joint Loans
							Board between 1988 and 1993 so that we can see the difference between
							the two?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Barmasai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the Joint Loans Board gave Kshs737,000 for the whole
							of that period. The KIE gave Kshs12,154,100.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Mwaura">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the Assistant Minister mentioned Kshs 24 million as
							money given out in form of a loan. Was this money given to Gachoka
							Constituency, Embu, or to the whole country?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Barmasai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the Question concerned Gachoka Constituency and,
							therefore, those figures are for Gachoka Constituency.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Nyagah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the Assistant Minister said that Kshs 24 million was
							extended to Gachoka. I have then asked him to give me a breakdown of
							this figure and he was very good to give me the breakdown as follows:-
							Kshs 737,000 in form of trade loans and Kshs 12 million. So is the
							Assistant Minister in order to mislead Kenyans that Kshs 24 million was
							given whereas in seven years, they only gave Kshs 12 million and Kshs
							700,000?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Barmasai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I was answering his supplementary question exactly as
							he asked it. He asked for the breakdown of the money for Kenya
							Industrial Estates (KIE) and Joint Loans Board. The balance is from
							ICDC.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que336">
					<title>TOURISM OFFICES IN NYAMIRA</title>
					<question by="Obwocha" to="MTI">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Obwocha asked the Minister for Tourism and Industry that in view of
							the increasing tourist attraction sites in Nyamira and the increasing
							fish farming, whether he could open offices in Nyamira Town.</p>
					</question>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Anybody from the Ministry of Tourism and Wildlife? We will come back to
							the Question later.<span class="unknown">Mr. Speaker</span> Next Question, Mr. Mutahi.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que514">
					<title>ISSUANCE OF SHARE CERTIFICATES</title>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Is Mr. Muhika not here? We will come back to the Question later.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que318">
					<title>REPAIRS OF AHERO-KISII ROAD</title>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Is Dr. Otieno-Kopiyo not here? We shall re-visit the Question later.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que602">
					<title>TARMACKING OF BUYANGU-EKERO ROAD</title>
					<question by="Shikuku" to="MPWH">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Shikuku asked the Minister for Public Works and Housing whether he
							will confirm that the Buyangu-Ekero Road is only being murrammed instead
							of being tarmacked as recommended by the Kakamega District Development
							Committee.</p>
					</question>
					<answer as="AMPWH" by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to reply.</p>
						<p>Odoo-Buyangu-Ekero Road was approved by the Kakamega District Development
							Committee (DDC) for tarmacking. Traffic census by the Ministry along
							this road indicate that the road does not meet the maximum requirement
							for tarmacking. Under the circumstances, therefore, it was decided that
							the road be murrammed. In fact, there is a contractor on site and the
							work is actually completed.</p>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, arising from that funny reply from the Assistant
							Minister, with a bit of truth in it, is he aware that this was a top
							priority of the DDC, Kakamega, and it was recommended many years ago
							based on the traffic on this road? Since when did this traffic reduce
							and this Government had a second thoughts?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, it is a pity that the hon. Member does not have the
							details with him. If he would be kind enough and accept correction, the
							traffic on that road averages 135 vehicles a day. As of today, the
							minimum requirement for any road to be tarmacked is 300 vehicles per
							day.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="LwaliOyondi">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, could the Assistant Minister deny or confirm that
							motorists are avoiding this road because it is in bad condition? If it
							had been tarmacked, everybody would be using it.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> I do not have to deny because I am not aware of that.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Karan">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, can the Assistant Minister tell this House how
							Eldama-Ravine - Eldoret Road qualifies to be tarmacked when the road is
							being used by goats?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, where I come from goats do not use roads.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Arising from that reply, is the Assistant Minister aware that I was a
							member of the DDC at that time and the DDC itself knew that there was
							enough traffic on that road and because of the bad state of the road,
							everybody avoided it? Now that in his reply he has said that the road
							will be completed by 30th September, 1995, is he aware that the road has
							not been completed? Which September is he talking about? This is October
							and the road is not completed. They are now murramming it. Is he in
							order to tell the house untruths? The road is not completed yet!</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, in my reply I said that the road is completed. If the
							hon. Member was in that DDC it is possible that he used undue influence
							to have the road passed when it did not qualify to be tarmacked.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. Do you accept that sort of
							innuendo from this Assistant Minister?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> No way, I will not accept it. Will you apologise? You are imputing
							improper motive.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kiluta">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I do apologise and ask the hon. Member to accept the
							answer given.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> For the second time, Mr. Kofa's Question.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que803">
					<title>BANDITRY MENACE IN GALOLE</title>
					<question by="Kofa" to="MS">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Kofa asked the Minister of State, Office of the President</p>
						<ul id="ul11">
							<li>whether he is aware that Councillor Abdi Sole of Asako Location was
								seriously injured and two homeguards were shot dead and their guns
								stolen while pursuing bandits on 20th May, 1995;</li>
							<li>who instructed these people to pursue the heavily armed bandits;
								and,</li>
							<li>whether he can ensure that the families of the deceased <span class="unknown">Mr. Kofa</span>
								homeguards are compensated and that Councillor Sole's medical
								expenses are paid in full.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer as="AMS" by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Speaker, Sir, I beg to apologise for not having answered the Question
							the first time. Now, I beg to give the following reply. </p>
						<p>I am aware that on 2nd June, 1995 and not on the 20th May, 1995,
							Councillor Abdi Sole of Asako Location in company of other councillors,
							assistant chief Mohammed Farah Wachu and home guards were attacked by
							bandits at a manyatta in Ditole area during which two home guards were
							shot dead and the councillor Sole injured. </p>
						<p>The assistant chief and the home guards were in normal security patrol of
							the area when they were attacked by the bandits and the question of
							compensation to the family of the deceased home guards and payment of
							medical expenses for councillor Abdi Sole is being studied in my office
							and appropriate action will be taken when this is over.</p>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Kofa">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I have not received the written reply, but if I
							listened carefully to the reply to part "b" of my Question, the
							Assistant Minister said "the chief and the home guards were in normal
							security patrol of the area". That means that the Assistant Minister has
							accepted that they got into problems while they were on duty. This
							councillor is maimed and can no longer fend for this family. Can the
							Assistant Minister confirm therefore that this maimed councillor and the
							two home guards that were killed will be compensated and could he tell
							us when this is going to be?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the hon. Member will appreciate that this incident
							involves the assistant chief, a homeguard as well as a politician and so
							on; and we are trying to study the legality of compensating each one of
							them. </p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Wako">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I would like to thank the Assistant Minister for the
							answer given that they are going to consider the case but how long will
							his consideration take because this is a problem which is affecting the
							whole of Northern Kenya?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the hon. Member who is a friend of mine will
							appreciate that if he came to the Office of the President this issue can
							always be speeded up and especially if he presents the case of his
							constituents fast enough.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Farah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Arising from the answer given by the Assistant Minister earlier in which
							he said that home guards are issued with fire arms under the Firearms
							Act which is not true because there is no provision in the Firearms Act
							to create militia. Could the Assistant Minister tell this House why we
							cannot have a crack anti-banditry squad which is saved and that is in a
							position to track down this bandits on foot instead of putting the lives
							of innocent Kenyans who do not have proper training at risk whereby they
							are killed by bandits.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> I hope hon. Farah is not actually implying that where he comes from they
							do need home guards. I am sure he does and he must also appreciate that
							in the past we have told him in this House that we are prepared to
							consider that possibility that he has presented.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Farah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. That undertaking was given by the
							Assistant Minister when I first came into this House three years ago.
							Could he tell us how much longer he needs to be given for him to select
							very modest young men from the existing forces who are Somalis,
							Turkanas, Masais or Pokots; people who are used to doing that kind of
							thing and use them as a crack squad to combact these bandits? How much
							longer does he need to constitute that small squad everywhere in the
							districts of the former NFD including Tana River?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> At least, the hon. Member has been honest enough to admit that we have
							given him the undertaking.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Kofa">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> After the killings of these two home guards and maiming the Councillors,
							the bandits took their guns away. A week later, these guns were brought
							by elders, which means these elders knew who the bandits were. What
							action has the Assistant Minister taken to arrest these bandits?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Sunkuli">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> We have not gotten the bandits yet. It is true the guns were
						recovered.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Falana">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. The Assistant Minister says that
							they have not apprehended the bandits yet, but the guns were recovered.
							Could he be transparent enough to tell this House how the guns were
							recovered without the bearers being there? If these bandits were not
							killed or captured, how did the elders get the guns?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> That is a supplementary question. Next Question, Mr. R.K. Mungai for the
							second time.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Mungai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, before I ask this Question, I beg to apologise to the
							House for not being here when the Question was first called.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que630b">
					<title>DEATH OF MS. MUIRURI</title>
					<question by="Mungai" to="MH">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. R.K. Mungai asked the Minister for Health</p>
						<ul id="ul12">
							<li>under what circumstances did the late Ms. <span class="unknown">Mr. R.K. Mungai</span> Anne
								Wairimu Mungai, aged 23 years, from Makuyu Location, Makuyu
								Constituency, die at the Thika District Hospital on Thursday 8th
								June, 1995 after being admitted under reference OBS/NO.4306; and, </li>
							<li>whether he could inform the House, the names, qualifications and
								relevant experience, respectively, of all the senior medical staff
								who attended the late Ms Anne Wairimu Muiruri of which I have not
								had a written reply.</li>
						</ul>
					</question>
					<answer as="MH" by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I hope the reply is on the way. I beg to reply. </p>
						<ul id="ul13">
							<li>The late Ms.---</li>
						</ul>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. It is about the answer being "on
							the way". According to the Standing Orders, the replies to Questions are
							supposed to be here five minutes before the sitting. When the bell
							rings, they are supposed to be here already. Now he is saying the answer
							is "on the way". Which way? How long will it take to reach here?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Order! Order! The Minister will reply to that, but to be honest with
							you, I do not even know how a question or an answer can be "on the
						way".</p>
					</speech>
					<answer as="MH" by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, his pigeonhole is part of the way. </p>
						<ul id="ul14">
							<li>I have quite a long answer because this involves the life of a
								person. The late Anne Wairimu Muiruri was admitted to Thika District
								Hospital Maternity Ward on 4th June, 1995 with obstructed labour.
								She had been in labour for a very long time at home and was only
								brought to the hospital after failing to deliver since the baby was
								too big and was lying in a breach position. She was prepared for
								caesarian section operation which was carried out a few hours later
								on the morning of 5th June, 1995. Post operatively, she developed
								bacterial infection due to prolonged obstructed labour at home. She
								was also diagnosed to have malaria. Despite antibiotics and
								anti-malaria treatment, her condition deteriorated and she died on
								the 8th June, 1995. However, the timely action by the medical staff
								saved the baby's life and we hope the baby is still alive. </li>
							<li>The name, qualifications and relevant experiences of the senior
								staff who attended the late Ms. Anne Wairimu Muiruri are here but
								the list is very long and I do not know whether I am supposed to
								read the whole of it. The team was led by a Consultant Dr. W. Mugo,
								a doctor of medicine for 11 years. Dr. Wachira, doctor of medicine
								for two years, Dr.---</li>
						</ul>
					</answer>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> You could Table the list.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Let me first use it to answer supplementary questions then I will Table
							it.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Mungai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> I do not have part of the information which the Minister was sort of
							reading in this reply. However, the reply has arrived eventually, but
							the Minister said certain things which I did quite follow, but which are
							not in the reply. Be that as it may, could the Minister confirm or deny
							that Ms. Muiruri died due to professional negligence on the part of
							those carrying out the operation? From the reply, it appears that she
							did not have any abnormal disease or complication and that malaria and
							bacterial infections could have been contained. Did the patient not have
							foreign bodies left in the operational area? Could the Minister confirm
							or deny this?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, I hope to deny that.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> As I was trying to read the list of the doctors who attended the late
							Ms. Muiruri, I heard him saying "so-and-so medical" and so on. Was there
							any gynaecologist among those doctors?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, there was a gynaecologist and also a midwife.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Farah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. The Minister is misleading the
							House. He says there was a gynaecologist and there is none in this list,
							it is all M.BP which are just the first general practitioners' degrees
							and there is no consultant on this. Was there a consultant
							gynaecologist?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> The lady needed midwives and there is a list of midwives and a surgeon.
							She did not need a gynaecologist.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="LwaliOyondi">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir. Is the Minister in order to
							mislead the House by calling midwives obstetrician/gynaecologist?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> I would be out of order if I did that.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Final question on that, Mr. Shikuku.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Shikuku">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Arising from the previous reply where the Minister is trying to dodge or
							go round the question, the question was, was any of those listed on that
							list a qualified gynaecologist? The answer after looking at the list is,
							there is none. Is he in order to mislead the House that there was a
							gynaecologist while there was none? If there was, what is his name?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Angatia">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, the lady needed midwives and surgeons. There were
							three surgeons and four midwives.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Farah">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> On a point of order, Mr. Speaker, Sir.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Order, I am sorry, hon. Farah. First of all, it is grossly out of order
							for you [Mr. Speaker]to imply that the Chair is wasting time. We are not
							also in the same breath going to turn this Chamber into a medical
							school.</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Mungai">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Mr. Speaker, Sir, can I ask the last supplementary question?</p>
					</speech>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Order! We do not operate that way; if you want to ask a question you
							stand up. </p>
						<p>Next Question.</p>
					</speech>
				</subdivision>
				<subdivision id="que336b">
					<title>TOURISM OFFICES IN NYAMIRA</title>
					<question by="Obwocha" to="MTW">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p>Mr. Obwocha asked the Minister for Tourism and Wildlife whether, in view
							of the increasing tourist sites in Nyamira and the increasing fish
							farming, the Ministry could open offices in Nyamira Town.</p>
					</question>
					<speech by="Smith" as="S">
						<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
						<p> Is there anybody from the Ministry of Tourism and Wildlife? Very well, I
							will now defer this Question to next week.</p>
					</speech>
					<comment>Question deferred</comment>
				</subdivision>
			</subdivision>
			<subdivision id="adjournement">
				<title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
				<speech by="Wetangula" as="TDS">
					<from>Mr. Kofa</from>
					<p>Order hon. Members! Tomorrow, hon. Dr. Kituyi, you must start with
						substantiation of that allegation. Hon. Members, the House stands adjourned
						until tomorrow, Wednesday, 1st November, 1995 at 9.00 a.m.</p>
				</speech>
			</subdivision>
		</debate>
		<conclusions>
			<p>The House rose at 6.30 p.m. <noteref href="#not01" num="3" /> </p>
		</conclusions>
	</debaterecord>
</akomantoso>
